https://www.troutmanlaw.com/tulsa-social-security-disability/terms-glossary/

Skip navigation.
Troutman & Troutman, P.C.
No Charge For Consultation
(918) 587-0050
Search for:
HomeAttorneys
Steve A. TroutmanGayle L. TroutmanDarren T. Rackley
Erin N. StackenwaltCharles R. HolladayVictoria Rackley
Let Us Review Your Case
Name *FirstLastPhone *Email *Message *Checkboxes *I have read and understand the Privacy Policy.PhoneSend Message
Disability
Evaluation
Do I Need a Disability Lawyer?Are You Working?
Can I Work While Receiving SSI or SSDI?Social Security Income Limits
Do You Have a Severe Impairment?Do You Have a Listed Impairment?
Drug and Alcohol Abuse
Can You Perform Your Last Relevant Work?Is There Any Work In the Regional or National Economy That You Can Perform?
Social Security’s Definition of DisabilityDisability Appeals Process
Social Security Disability Hearing
Benefits
Can You Lose Disability Benefits?Social Security Disability Back PayDisability Benefits for VeteransHow to Calculate Social Security Disability Benefits
DeterminationDisability TermsApplying for Disability in OklahomaSocial Security Death BenefitsThe Difference Between SSD and SSI
Eligibility for SSDI and MedicareSSI and Medicaid Eligibility
Contingency Fees in SSD CasesSocial Security FAQs
Let Us Review Your Case
Name *FirstLastPhone *Email *Message *Checkboxes *I have read and understand the Privacy Policy.MessageSend Message
Video Library
Meet The AttorneysSocial Security BenefitsDisability Law
Let Us Review Your Case
Name *FirstLastPhone *Email *Message *Checkboxes *I have read and understand the Privacy Policy.CommentSend Message
BlogContact Us
Troutman & Troutman, P.C.1350 South Boulder AvenueSuite 410Tulsa, Oklahoma 74119
Phone: (918) 587-0050
Toll Free: (888) 549-0050
Fax: (918) 587-0006
Click here for directions
Let Us Review Your Case
Name *FirstLastPhone *Email *Message *Checkboxes *I have read and understand the Privacy Policy.EmailSend Message
Search for:
Top Disability Terms in SSDI and SSI Cases
Social Security Disability Lawyer in Tulsa OK Defines Common Phrases, Terms and Abbreviations
Our Tulsa disability attorneys understand how complicated the Supplement Security Income (SSI) and Social Security Disability Insurance (SSDI) process can be. When filling out paperwork or reading information about benefits, some words may be unfamiliar.
With this in mind, below is a glossary of commonly used terms by the Social Security Administration (SSA) when describing disability benefits.
Disability Terms to Know
ALJ
Alleged Onset of Disability
Appeal
Application for Disability Benefits
Benefit Verification Letter
Claimant
Consultative Examination
ALJ, or Administration Law Judge
When you are appealing a benefit decision, you may have a hearing before an ALJ, who can award you benefits.
Back to Top
Alleged Onset of Disability, or Alleged Onset Date
The date you claim your inability to work began used to determine retroactive back pay, which is discussed below.
Back to Top
Appeal, or Disability Claim Appeal
When applying for benefits, you will receive a letter from the SSA explaining its determination of your eligibility. If the agency determines that you are not eligible SSDI, then an appeals process exists that includes hearings before ALJs and an Appeals Council.
Back to Top
Application for Disability Benefits
If you were to receive SSDI, then you must complete and sign an initial application. On the application, the SSA will ask you questions about your functionality as well as your disabilities. It may also require verification or evidence of your condition.
Back to Top
Benefit Verification Letter
A letter that verifies the amount an individual receives each month in benefits, usually sent at the request of a beneficiary.
Back to Top
Claimant, or Applicant
The term used to describe the person seeking Social Security benefits.
Back to Top
Consultative Examination
A medical exam that the SSA may require to process a benefit claim.
Back to Top
COLA, or Cost of Living Adjustment
Social Security recipients may receive a cost-of-living adjustment or raise in benefits based on inflation.
Back to Top
Credits, or Social Security Credits
When you work, you earn credits that then count toward your eligibility for future Social Security benefits, including SSDI.
Back to Top
Decision Notice, or Award Letter or Denial Letter
The letter generated by the SSA informing you of a benefit decision.
Back to Top
Family Maximum
The maximum amount of benefits paid to an entire family on a worker’s record.
Back to Top
FICA Tax, or Federal Insurance Contributions Act Tax
The tax that is withheld from paychecks for funding Social Security and Medicare programs.
Back to Top
Income
Earnings used to determine benefit amounts including:
Earned Income – Wages and money from self–employment, royalties, honoraria and sheltered workshop payments
Unearned Income – Such as Social Security benefits, pensions, state disability payments and unemployment benefits
In–Kind Income – Income considered to be for food or shelter that you get for free or less than fair market value
Deemed Income – From a spouse, parent or sponsor, which could be used to compute benefits
Back to Top
Listings of Impairments
Many conditions are listed in a manual known as the “Blue Book,” which contains information for about processes through which disability determinations are decided.
Back to Top
Maximum Earnings
The maximum amount of earnings the SSA can count in any calendar year when computing benefits totals.
Back to Top
Number Holder
A wage earner or person who earns Social Security credits.
Back to Top
OASDI, or Old Age Survivors and Disability Insurance
The SSA’s retirement program that is separate from SSDI and SSI—this can be confusing, as the program is often referred to simply as “Social Security.”
Back to Top
Payment Date
The day on which your payments are allotted each month depends on different factors. To view the SSA’s payment schedule, you can click here.
Back to Top
POMS, or Program Operations Manual System
Source of information Social Security employees use to process claims for benefits.
Back to Top
Proofs
Documents submitted by individuals applying for benefits and services, including birth certificates, marriage certificates, W2 forms, tax returns as well as deeds. Most documents must be original copies or certified.
Back to Top
Representative Payee
If someone is unable to handle their own financial affairs, then the SSA may appoint a relative, a friend or an interested party to handle payments.
Back to Top
Retroactive Benefits, or Back Pay
To determine back pay, the SSA uses criteria including the date at which you were disabled, the application date and the waiting period, which is the period that takes place between when you apply.
Back to Top
Supplemental Security Income (SSI)
These benefits are available to low-income individuals who have not worked or do not have credits. If you are not eligible for SSDI, then this may be an option for you.
Back to Top
Survivors Benefits
Benefits paid to widows, children and parents for people who died after earning sufficient work credits.
Back to Top
Reach Out to Our Tulsa SSDI Attorneys If You Have Questions about Disability Benefits
For more information and a free evaluation, then call (918) 587-0050 or fill out the case review form today. Our Tulsa SSDI lawyers work on a contingency fee basis, meaning we do not collect money unless we succeed in obtaining you benefits. Our attorney fees are regulated by the SSA and come only from the past-due disability benefits we recover on your behalf. All future monthly payments are yours to keep!
Questions? Call (800) 318-2596
Point of Interest If you have received a letter from the SSA that is confusing, are in the process of applying for benefits or appealing a decision, contact our Tulsa SSDI law firm for experienced guidance.
Let Us Review Your Case Name *FirstLastPhone *Email *Message *Checkboxes *I have read and understand the Privacy Policy.EmailSend Message
Category Feed
For a free consultation Call (918) 587-0050 or (888) 549-0050Fax: (918) 587-0006
1350 South Boulder AvenueSuite 410 Tulsa, Oklahoma 74119
Sitemap
Privacy Policy
© 2012–2020 Troutman & Troutman, P.C.
Law Firm Marketing by
